VII

At the Mansion House

As I followed the girl through the hall, a man’s voice asked,

“Is that O’Brien?”

“No,” she said, “it’s someone to see you, father.”

She showed me into a room and closed the door, and in the course of the next few minutes I came to one or two pretty obvious conclusions. She was clearly Mr. Rendall’s daughter, and they were equally clearly in the habit of receiving visits at odd times from Mr. O’Brien; in fact they evidently concluded it was he, or Miss Rendall herself would scarcely have opened the door to me. Also, her reply might be taken as implying that if Mr. O’Brien had been the visitor, it would not have been her father he had come to see. But whether or no this were the true interpretation, I so thoroughly disliked and suspected O’Brien that any suggestion of intimacy was alone enough to make me glad I had started on the defensive.

“Otherwise,” said I to myself, “what a charming girl to find in such a place!”

However, I reminded myself that I had not come here to be charmed, and proceeded next to take stock of the room.

It was not large, but pleasantly proportioned, low in the ceiling, and pervaded with a delicate yet distinct flavour of the past. I found myself instinctively wondering how one could reproduce this particular flavour on the stage; no armour or tapestry or any of the usual antique paraphernalia to be allowed, for beyond the thick walls and rather small windows, it was so difficult to lay one’s finger on any one specific thing that palpably suggested age. Finally I decided that it was impossible to recreate such an atmosphere. It was compounded of stillness within and the glimpses of primeval quiet without, of a touch of comfortable shabbiness, of plenty of elderly books, and of a faint odour of the dampness of centuries mingled with the scent of honeysuckle. My suspicions were suddenly lulled, and with that prompt decision which has landed me in and pulled me out of so many holes, I decided to drop my German accent. That the charming Miss Rendall might miss it, and wonder what had become of it, was (I must confess) a reflection which did not occur to me till afterwards.

Just as I had come to this decision, in walked the laird, and in two minutes I had come to another decision, which was to adhere to the plan of campaign I had thought of as I walked, in so far as keeping my business to myself was concerned. My first impression of Mr. Rendall was of height, and a certain quiet, formidable quality. He was grey-haired, with a close-clipped grizzled moustache, loose clothes as though he had shrunk a little in girth, and the unmistakable air of a man who had seen considerably more of the world than the island of Ransay. He received me quite politely and hospitably, but with every moment that passed I grew more acutely conscious of something deterrent behind his courtesy. A sense of a strong personality in the background, not actually hostile as yet, but ironic and critical, set me instinctively and instantly on guard. Not that I actually suspected the man; but to take him straightway into my confidence was simply impossible. A man of another temperament might have done so—and quite possibly have been right; but his effect on me was like tapping a limpet.

I gave him my name and then I said in a quiet confidential way,

“Forgive this intrusion, Mr. Rendall, but the fact is my ship has evidently been called away.”

I glanced towards the window, and following my look he could see the smoke of the cruiser just visible on the horizon. He gave a little nod but said nothing.

“I was landed last night on a certain piece of business,” I went on, “and it is no part of that business to make myself conspicuous, and so I have taken the liberty of coming to your house.”

“You wish to wait here till your ship returns?” he enquired.

“I thought perhaps you might know of some lodging where I might remain quietly.”

He smiled slightly.

“You had better stay here. There is no other lodging.”

I began to thank him, but he cut me short.

“It is Hobson’s choice,” said he, “and my house is not overcrowded at present. Have you lunched?”

“I am afraid I haven’t.”

“Come and join us. My daughter and I had just sat down.”

He moved towards the door.

“I have no luggage,” I said.

“I can lend you what you want.”

I thanked him again, and said brazenly,

“May I ask for the loan of a coat. I am anxious not to exhibit my uniform coat in the island if I can help it.”

I thought he looked a trifle surprised (it must be remembered that all this time I was in a buttoned-up oilskin), but he merely nodded again and led me upstairs to a pleasant bedroom with a low ceiling and some heavy old-fashioned mahogany furniture. There he left me and in a moment returned with a brush and comb and a tweed coat.

I had noticed that in one of the drawers there was a key, and as I took the coat I said,

“I hope you won’t think me unduly cautious if I lock my uniform coat up in one of these drawers. There are certain papers in the pockets which I am bound to be careful of.”

Again I fancied I caught a brief look of surprise, but it must have been very brief, for his face was as inscrutable as ever as he answered,

“Do exactly as you like.”

A maid came with a jug of hot water and then I was alone.

“I wonder if the man believes me?” I said to himself. “Things are going a little too dashed smoothly!”

However, there was nothing for it now but playing the game out. I first took the precaution of suddenly and quietly opening the door. There was nobody at the key hole, so I took off my oilskin and put on the tweed coat, and then locked up the top drawer and put the key in my pocket. Hardly necessary to say that drawer remained as empty as the others.

“I call that either a very neat dodge, or a devilish silly one,” I said to myself. “And which it is depends entirely on the results.”

As I brushed my hair I thanked my stars I was fair, for a shave was now long overdue.

“What a pirate I’d look if I were a brunette!” I thought, and as it was, the recollection of dainty Miss Rendall made me determined to borrow a razor forthwith.

I foresaw that lunch would be a function demanding considerable tact. Seeing that I had decided, rightly or wrongly (and the Lord knew which!), not to trust these people, they had to be kept in a nice equilibrium betwixt doubt and confidence. To persuade them too thoroughly that they were entertaining a genuine British naval officer would be fatal if they were treasonably inclined, and a serious mistake if they were not, for then they might reassure the other islanders and my gang would go to earth, not to be dug up again in a hurry. On the other hand, to have them too suspicious would be all right if they were treasonable, but would probably end my adventure if they were honest.

The line I selected was a blend of mystery regarding my business, breezy chat on noncommittal topics, and an occasional oddity of conduct, such as might have been caused by a guilty conscience or a harmless strain of eccentricity (and I left them to make their choice).

Here are a few choice excerpts from our conversation, which I happen to remember more or less verbatim.

Myself | Chattily. “Delightful air you have in your island! Like champagne—or perhaps in these parts I ought to say like whisky and soda.”
Mr. Rendall | Somewhat drily. “We do happen to be acquainted with champagne.”
Miss Rendall | Smiling pleasantly as she ate. “We probably don’t look as though we were, father. Mr. Merton’s metaphor was safer.”
Myself | Feeling rather an ass, but outwardly gay. “I meant no reflection on your cellar, Miss Rendall. I was merely aiming at local colour.”

At this point I fell abruptly silent, the laugh, as it were, frozen on my lips. I gazed at my plate and then glanced furtively at my host (I was giving them their choice). The next fragment of conversation which I remember ran somewhat thus:—

Myself | Leading up deliberately to the test question. “There’s one thing I envy the natives of this happy island. What a wonderful show of wild flowers they have! Do they make good grazing?”
Mr. Rendall | Again drily. “If one happens to have ruminant tastes, I believe they are edible.”
Miss Rendall | Brightly, but evidently unkindly. “Mr. Merton was probably thinking chiefly of the ruminant natives.”
Myself | Keeping sternly to the point. “I was thinking chiefly of sheep.” With a direct and steady look at the laird. “Are there many sheep on this island?”
Mr. Rendall | Quite calmly. “A good many. Are you anxious for statistics?”
Myself | Concealing my disappointment under a brave smile. “Oh no. Please don’t mistake me for an intelligent enquirer.”

I turned the brave smile on to Miss Rendall. She smiled back very slightly. In her face I seemed to read a trace of scepticism; as if she did not quite agree with my modest estimate of myself, but at the same time thought none the better of me. I would have given a good deal to know exactly what was in her mind. Did she suspect something? And if so, what?

I had one more shot. It was an inspiration which came to me at the end of lunch when my host offered me a cigar.

“Matches?” he observed, pushing a box towards me.

Again I looked at him hard and asked,

“Have you such a thing as a wax match?”

His eyebrows rose slightly.

“If you prefer to light a cigar with a wax match I daresay I can find one.”

“If Mr. Merton doesn’t mind waiting for half an hour perhaps I might discover a box in the store room,” said Miss Rendall, and she added demurely, “beside the champagne.”

My only consolation was that I was making an idiot of myself in a good cause.

X

The Coast Patrol

That evening we were all three sitting in the library (the same old-world room into which I had first been shown), when a servant entered and gave a message to Mr. Rendall. He rose and went out, leaving his daughter and myself each apparently immersed in a book. She may genuinely have been, but I was making the covers of mine a screen for inward debate. Had I made a mere fool of myself and should I make a clean breast of everything to my hosts? Or should I wait a little longer before deciding? I went on thinking after the laird had left the room, and Miss Jean still kept her eyes immovably on her page. I frankly confess I have never cut less ice with any woman—especially one who decidedly attracted me.

In a few minutes her father returned and said to her:

“John Howiseon has cried off tonight. I must go myself.”

She started up with a word of expostulation, but he merely smiled in his grim way, nodded at her (not at me, I noticed) and was gone. With a little sigh she sat down again and plunged into her book, but my curiosity had been roused and in a moment I enquired,

“Is your father going out for long?”

Her concern seemed to have broken down her reticence.

“All night,” she said. “I wish he wouldn’t!”

“What’s the matter?” I asked.

“The coast patrol,” said she.

“The coast patrol!” I exclaimed. “What’s that?”

She seemed to look at me for an instant a little doubtfully before she answered,

“The Admiralty have asked all the Justices of Peace to have the coast patrolled.”

“By whom?”

“Anybody they can get. We have the whole island mapped out into beats and the different farmers take it night about.”

For the moment I only half believed her. Such an amateur way of keeping watch and ward in such a vital area seemed hardly credible, but I learned afterwards that in those early days of the war that was one of the things which actually happened. Another fact also made me doubtful. On the night I landed I had met no watchers.

“Who watches the shore up at the north end—near the Scollays’ farm?” I asked.

“Oh, Dr. Rendall and Mr. O’Brien look after that beat,” said she.

In a flash my belief in my own adventure had begun to return. Either that couple neglected their duty—or I had met one of the watchers!

“Do the doctor and Mr. O’Brien ever go out themselves—like your father tonight?” I asked.

“Mr. O’Brien goes out pretty often, I believe.”

I thought for a moment longer and then I jumped up.

“This seems the very job for an able-bodied young man,” I said with a laugh. “I’m going out to join the watchers!”

“You!” she exclaimed, springing up too.

I looked her straight in the eye.

“Why not me?” I enquired.

She said nothing for an instant, and then she remarked in quite a matter of fact voice,

“Very well; if you are going, I’ll come with you.”

I could not resist parodying her.

“You!” I exclaimed.

But I got no smile in response.

“I’ll be ready in five minutes,” she said as she left the room.

“Now what the devil does this mean?” I said to myself.

Five minutes of course meant quarter of an hour, and then we sallied forth into the night, she in a long tweed coat and I in my inevitable oilskin.

“Which way do you want to go?” she asked.

“Suppose we work our way towards the north end,” I suggested.

She said nothing more and we made our way by a track to the shore and then turned toward the left. I had been filling my pipe and when we got to the last stone wall, I stopped, bent under its shelter and struck a match. My face was towards her and in the fraction of a second before the first match blew out I caught a glimpse of something just visible in the mouth of one of the big pockets of her tweed coat. It was the butt end of a pistol.

I struck three more matches before I got my pipe alight and I contrived to face her each time, but she had turned and kept her other side towards me. When we resumed our walk I noticed that she consistently kept two or three yards away from me.

“Just shooting distance!” I said to myself.

“By the way, what are we supposed to be looking for?” I enquired presently.

“Chiefly periscopes, I think,” said she.

I stopped short and gazed over the inky sea.

“Do they light them up for us?” I asked.

She laughed despite herself.

“That is what I’ve been wondering myself,” said she.

This was her only sympathetic relapse, and to tell the truth I made no further remarks worthy of being smiled at. That pistol kept me thinking. That she had come out to watch me, and if necessary shoot me, seemed a pretty obvious deduction, and much as I admired her nerve, it made humorous conversation a trifle difficult.

On we walked, on and on for what seemed an interminable distance. It was quite moonless and only a few stars twinkled here and there through a veil of light clouds that had drifted up with the sunset. The grass underfoot was black, the sea was nearly as dark, and the inland country invisible. Once I remarked:

“It’s a curious thing that we haven’t met any of our fellow watchers.”

“The beats are very long,” she said, “and I’m afraid all the watchers don’t keep at their posts all the time.”

“What; they take a nap now and then?”

She seemed as though she were going to agree, and then to change her mind.

“Oh, we shall meet someone very soon. I think father is taking this beat.”

But we met no one, and as we pursued our lonely way I began to think that here was quite a possible reason for my not having come upon one of these coast patrols two nights ago. Still, it was only a possible reason; the other alternative remained.

And then, I know not how it was, but I began gradually to get a curious impression that something was in the air, something was going to happen. It is easy to say I only imagine now in the retrospect that I had this feeling. But I noted the sensation clearly and positively at the time. I strained my eyes, I looked this way and that, so strong did the feeling become. Once I thought for a moment I heard soft footsteps somewhere on the inland side and I stopped short then and listened, but when I stopped I heard nothing.

It can only have been a few minutes after this that the figure at my side (which had been so silent that I had almost forgotten it was a girl, and a pretty girl too) stopped suddenly, and I stood still beside her.

“Do you hear anything?” she asked, and there seemed to be a little catch in her breath.

I listened and shook my head. I could see that she was gazing intently down at the beach.

“Do you see anything?” I asked in a voice instinctively hushed.

“No,” she answered in the same low tone, “but I thought I heard something.”

Again I strained my ears, and this time I distinctly did hear something; it might have been a movement among the rocks below, or on the bank ahead of us. She said nothing more but she seemed to be peering down into the gloom that veiled the beach.

“I’ll go down and see what it is,” I said.

For an instant I thought she was going to demur, but she said nothing, and with a bold air I stepped off the turf and began to make my way down, first through loose boulders and then along a ledge below. I confess frankly that I felt a trifle less bold than I looked, especially when I discovered the hazardous nature of the going. I remember that the sky began to seem lighter by contrast, but that the rocks were sheer chaotic darkness.

I must have been feeling my way along for some minutes, with a growing sense of the futility of the performance, when I first heard the sharp tinkle of a loose stone on rock. I turned towards the sound and heard it again. Either three or four times I had heard it distinctly when I found myself close to the grass again, only at this place there was a steep little cliff, higher than my head, between it and me, instead of a slope of boulders, so that anyone on the bank above would be looking straight down on to me. All this I can swear to.

And then when my shoulder was rubbing this low cliff face, I thought—indeed I am sure—I heard something move above, and certainly there was a sharp grating sound on the rock at my back; within an inch of me, it seemed. I looked round quickly just in time to catch a glimpse of something thin and curved and sinister passing upwards, against the night sky. I did not see it descend again, but the next moment came the sharp grating, close to my head this time, and once more the long curved menace passed up, faintly visible against the sky.

I did not wait for it to descend again. That somebody was striking at me from above and that I had better get out of the way seemed so evident that I spent no further time in watching the operation. I started from the cliff, my foot struck a patch of seaweed, and with a half smothered “Damn!” I did the next few yards sliding seawards on my side. A peculiarly hard ledge stopped my career and for a moment I lay there wondering what bones were broken. By the time I had found there were none, and scrambled to my feet, the sky line above the bank was clear. Whoever had struck at me was gone and there was not even the slightest sound, save the gurgling of the sea below. And then I gingerly picked my way back.

I drew near the turf bank at the top and now again I stopped. Low voices reached my ear distinctly and presently I spied two vague forms standing close together. Before I moved again I had transferred something from my hip pocket to my oilskin jacket and I kept my hand there too, closed upon it and ready. Then I advanced.

“Is that you, Mr. Merton?” said a voice I knew.

“It is, Mr. Rendall,” I answered drily.

“Did you see anybody?”

“No,” I answered truthfully.

“We thought we heard a cry,” said Miss Jean.

“I may have startled a sea gull,” I suggested; and then I asked with a sharpness in my voice I could not quite control, “Where did Mr. Rendall spring from?”

“I told you I thought we should meet him,” she answered, with a cool note in her voice that countered mine.

“What a curious chance that we should all meet here!” I exclaimed.

“It is precisely what I expected,” said she.

“Did you think then it was Mr. Rendall down among the rocks?” I enquired.

“No,” she said, “and it wasn’t.”

“Oh,” I replied in a tone which (if I achieved my intention) might have meant anything—or nothing.

Her father had been standing perfectly silent during this bout, a towering figure muffled in a heavy ulster and scarf, with the rim of his hat turned down over his face. Now he spoke in his dry caustic way,

“Have you had enough exercise, Mr. Merton?”

“Quite, thank you.”

“Then we can all go back together.”

He turned and his daughter took his arm. I walked behind them—it seemed on the whole safer, and I kept my hand in my pocket all the while.

I had seen no one, it is true; I had heard no sound that could be sworn to as made by a human being, the thing I saw so dimly might possibly not have been a lethal weapon (and if it was a weapon, what in Heaven’s name could it be? I wondered); it might conceivably have been a large bird some distance off, just as by a reverse illusion men are said to have fired at bumble bees when grouse driving. Also, it was within the bounds of possibility that the tinkling stones might not have been thrown down by someone above in order to draw me under that face. Everything had been so vague that all these alternatives were conceivable. But my own mind was quite and finally determined now that my adventure with the stranger on the shore had been no figment of my fancy, and I felt sure moreover that they had made up their minds about me and decided to act. How and why they had come to such a definite conclusion despite all my efforts to mislead them, beat me at first completely. And then I stopped short and almost shouted “Idiot!”

I had addressed Miss Rendall at her own door in a German accent. Then I had abruptly dropped it and through all my deliberate mystifications one fact had been clear—that I spoke in the accents of an ordinary more or less educated Englishman. The Rendalls clearly had the material for coming to a conclusion, and now in their company I had all but ended my days on earth.

Yet somehow or other now that I saw all this so clearly, I found myself singularly reluctant to accept the logical conclusion that this gentleman of good lineage and standing and this attractive high-spirited girl were actually traitors of the basest sort, and murderous traitors too.

“Hang it, I may be wrong after all!” I said to myself. “I know I’m young: I am told I’m rash; I have made a fool of myself periodically as long as I’ve known myself, I’ll give them the benefit of the doubt a little longer.”

At the door Mr. Rendall left us to resume his conscientious patrol. I said a brief and cool good night to Jean, went up to my room and tumbled straight into bed.

“In the morning I’ll think things over,” I decided.

VI

The Spectacled Man

It was, I remember, on a rare day of bright, still, frosty weather, that Mr. Hobhouse returned a little late for the doctor’s midday dinner. The garrulous creature was looking thoughtful and, as it were, subdued; wanting a dram, no doubt, thought any who chanced to spy him in this unusual condition. But as he opened the front door he became his foolish self instantaneously. The sound of a strange voice had reached him distinctly.

“Let me introduce Captain Whiteclett—Mr. Hobhouse,” said the doctor.

He and the stranger had already begun dinner, and Commander Whiteclett rose and bowed politely. Mr. Hobhouse bowed still more politely and having the advantage of being at the doctor’s back for the moment, was able to embellish his low obeisance with several curious facial expressions. The Commander at the same moment was attacked with a sharp bout of coughing, but presently recovering, the meal proceeded very pleasantly.

It appeared that Commander Whiteclett was visiting the island in the course of a tour of inspection, and having some acquaintance with the doctor had dropped in for lunch. He seemed pleased to meet Mr. Hobhouse and was as affable as naval officers always are, though every now and then it might have been noticed by a very close observer that after meeting that gentleman’s eye, he showed a tendency to stare suddenly out of the window for several moments. Mr. Hobhouse on his part was in his most gushing humour, and in fact chatted almost continuously through the meal.

As they passed out of the dining room ahead of the doctor, the two guests exchanged a whisper, and about quarter of an hour later Mr. Hobhouse declared that he must set forth and resume his antiquarian researches, and effusively bade the Commander goodbye. Thereupon the Commander said he also must be off and wondered in which direction his fellow guest was walking. It chanced that they were both going the same way and so they departed together.

“Well, you ridiculous looking dipsomaniac, how do you like water for dinner?” enquired the Commander when they were safely out of earshot.

“It lies cold on the tummy,” said I, “and if you’ve brought a flask, Jack—”

“I have,” said my cousin, “but wait a bit till there are no witnesses. And by the way, old chap, I must tell you that you’re a d⸺d good actor.”

“My photograph has appeared in the Tatler” I confessed.

“And what news?” he asked.

“Up till this morning I should have said ‘none.’ My dear Jack, it has been the most hopelessly baffling business you can possibly imagine. I think I am quite a success as an alcoholic patient, and also accepted by this time as the typical harmless antiquary. So I am able to wander all over the place and talk to everybody, but there has been nothing to take hold of! I have seen no sign of anything happening—” I caught his eye and asked quickly, “Has anything happened?”

He nodded.

“Signalling night before last and a submarine seen yesterday that we suspect of having been here.”

“Under my nose!” I groaned. “A fat lot of good I am!”

“My dear chap, you can’t possibly watch the whole coast all night and every night. This time the signals were seen from the sea as a matter of fact. But you can note the night, and also the hour, which was 2:45 a.m., G.M.T., as near as I can make out from the report. By the way, you had better set your watch by mine now while we remember. Possibly you may be able to discover who was out at that hour night before last.”

“I may, but it’s a thousand to one against it. Give me a thousand such chances, and I’ll get him! That’s just about how it seems to work out so far.”

“Haven’t you got any new ideas?”

“Without new evidence, what new ideas can one get? And I only got my first piece of evidence this morning. In fact, I haven’t had time to think it over yet.”

“Let’s hear it,” said my cousin keenly.

“I have been on the track of that old boy with spectacles, as being the only definite thing to look for so far. I did what Bolton did—went to see every old man in the place, and this morning I polished off the last of them and came to the same conclusion as he did. There is no such old gentleman on the island. But there was one, for a short time one morning; and he was a fake like Thomas Sylvester Hobhouse; and this morning I’ve heard of someone else who saw him!”

“By Gad!” exclaimed my cousin. “That sounds like the beginning of business.”

“Only the beginning, I’m afraid. This morning I interview my last old man—to find of course he wasn’t the fellow I was after. I interviewed him on the usual subject—ancient traditions of the island, and from that we passed on to the latest tradition, the legend of the mysterious visitor last August. He told me all about it, with many embellishments. However he was shrewd enough not to believe all he heard, and to show me what absurd stories are put about, he informed me that his own small granddaughter, aged six, had declared that she had seen the mysterious visitor, only she described him as having a white beard and funny spectacles. I asked him exactly where this phenomenon had been observed, and by Jingo, Jack, it was at the very place I met him; only when she saw him he had left the road and was hurrying down to the sea. She described him as running, which finally demolished her reputation for truthfulness, for as her grandfather observed, men of his age don’t run. But that was my friend right enough!”

“Heading for the sea?”

“For the beach, I take it. You see you can pop over the edge almost anywhere along that shore, and get out of sight among the rocks in a moment. I presume he squatted down there, pocketed his spectacles and beard, took off his disreputable overcoat, and either hid it or possibly pinned up the skirts and put it on under his other coat, and walked off looking like—well, that’s the rub, what did he look like then? And that’s just where I seem no forrader.”

“Still, this is something.”

“Yes, and I suppose we ought to deduce something more from the episode. I’ve already concluded that the high piping voice he used might well have concealed an accent, and I’ve also decided from what I’ve heard of the local language since that he hadn’t the native intonation.”

“And he headed for the beach,” added my cousin. “Therefore he certainly did not come from any house in the near neighbourhood.”

“That puts the doctor’s house out of court, if you’re right. But he may possibly have thought it better not to do his dressing up at home.”

“I see you’ve still got you knife into O’Brien!” laughed my cousin. “But I think my notion is the likeliest—”

He broke off suddenly and we instinctively moved a pace further apart. A figure had appeared round a turn of the road just ahead of us, a trim, dainty figure, delightful to see in such a place, but a little disconcerting to see so suddenly and so close to us. It was Jean Rendall, looking her best, but not, it seemed to me, quite in the right place.

Had she noticed anything? There was not a sign of it in her greeting. She gave us both one of her quick smiles, and as Jack pulled up to speak to her, she stopped too, and in talking to him, I noticed afresh how full of expression those neatly chiselled, rather petite, features became when she talked, and what a charming little air of knowing her way about the world she had. Young though she was, I could see in her very clearly either a valuable friend or a dangerous enemy—and what an easy girl to fall in love with, had circumstances been very different!

Jack explained in a very natural offhand manner how he came to be in Mr. Hobhouse’s company, and Mr. Hobhouse corroborated his statement in his own effusive way. And then as we parted, she threw her smile full on that gentleman, and asked,

“Why haven’t you been to see us again, Mr. Hobhouse? Do come to tea one day!”

Mr. Hobhouse gabbled a polite but slightly, evasive reply, and we walked on.

“Do you mean to say,” demanded my cousin, “that you have only been to see this delectable lady once?”

“That’s all,” I admitted.

“What’s the reason? It isn’t very like our methods, Roger.”

“It isn’t,” I admitted again. “But then you see what with pestilential weather and all these antiquarian visits to pay, my available time has been pretty well occupied.”

“But that house is one to keep a particular eye on.”

“That house has got a pair of particularly bright eyes in it. On my one visit there I felt a little too like walking on the edge of a precipice to wish to repeat the experience often. If that girl suspects me, Jack, and if she isn’t the right sort, we are dished.”

“Oh, dash it. I can’t believe she’s mixed up in this business!” he declared. “Of course one mustn’t trust anybody; still, that doesn’t prevent your going to tea with her. In fact what you really ought to be doing is making love to her—so long as you keep your head.”

“I am handicapped,” I pointed out, “by drunken habits, a beard, and Mother Beagle’s Beautiful Black Dye. No, Jack, I do not see orange blossom this trip.”

“Apart from these romantic dreams,” persisted my cousin, “she is far more likely to be inquisitive about you if you never go near the house. In fact I could see it in her eye today.”

“Well,” I said, “I’ll call tomorrow and dispel her interest in me.”

Since my talk with the doctor, his theory about Jean Rendall had crossed my mind occasionally, and improbable as it was, I thought I might as well test it.

“By the way,” I asked, “did you by any chance ever speak to Miss Rendall about my last visit to the island?”

His look of surprise was a sufficient answer in itself.

“Speak to her of your adventure? Not a word at any time! Why?”

“The doctor has an idea that she knows more than she says, and that you may have told her something.”

“Rubbish!”

“I knew it was,” I assured him.

And so that possibility was finally eliminated.

We thought it wiser that our ways should part some little distance from the pier.

“Good-luck, old chap,” said he, shaking my hand. “Keep playing the game you’re at and don’t worry about trying to keep a lookout at nights. That’s being done already, and though I don’t believe the fellows are much use—not with such crafty devils against them—you can’t do anything to help ’em. Getting out at night is too risky, and you’re too far away at the house. Your game is to work it from the other end. Sooner or later they are absolutely bound to give you a clue.”

His spirit and my little discovery of the morning sent me back in a distinctly more hopeful mood.

XIII

Jean’s Guesses

“Come into father’s room and then you can smoke,” said Jean.

It was the same pleasant, well-remembered room into which she had shown me that day when I first made her acquaintance, and as I followed her in now it struck me forcibly that I had taken the wrong turning that August morning. If I had taken these people into my confidence then, I should at least have started on the right road. Better than ever I realised what tricks my instincts play me. Or perhaps it may be my efforts to regulate them by the light of what I am pleased to call my reason that produce such unhappy results.

“I am wondering how they found you out,” she began. “It seems so mysterious that they should have suddenly started to try and murder you like that. They must have felt quite positive—and what made them feel positive?”

“Did you or your father say anything to anybody about my voice; that I didn’t seem to have so much accent as I had at first, or anything of that kind?”

“Not a word,” she said positively. “Father is the most uncommunicative of people, and I have inherited some of his closeness.”

“Your servants?” I suggested.

“They are Ransay girls, and one foreign accent is the same as another to them,” she laughed.

“Then it must have been finding the parachute. I always thought that gave me away.”

“But it wasn’t found till Monday morning, after we had been for that walk.”

“It might have been found by these people sooner.”

“It might,” she admitted without much conviction. “But still—who did you see or speak to apart from us and Dr. Rendall and Mr. O’Brien?”

“The Scollays,” I said, “and several farmers I happened to meet; but always with a most suspicious accent. Oh, and there was one incident I forgot to mention. On the Sunday afternoon I was doing a little fancy shooting with my revolver down on the beach when Jock turned up. You know Jock the idiot?”

“Well,” she said, but her attention had evidently been caught by my first words. “You were doing fancy shooting,” she repeated. “Are you a very good shot?”

“Quite useful,” I admitted with becoming modesty. “That afternoon I was rather above myself.”

“Then,” she cried, “you were seen, and that’s why the man stopped firing at you as soon as you aimed at him! He knew he would be hit if he went on!”

I opened my eyes a little and smiled.

“That is a flattering solution,” I said, “but if I may venture to say so, it seems rather a bold inference.”

“I’m certain it’s right,” she said confidently. “Did you speak to Jock?”

“Yes, I had a little talk with him; that’s to say of course I did all the talking.”

“In your natural voice?”

“Latterly I did,” I admitted.

“Were you far from the wall above the beach.”

“Not very.”

“And I suppose there were lots of rocks about?”

“The usual supply.”

“Then someone was behind either the wall or the rocks and you were overheard! That’s how you were found out!”

“Miss Rendall,” I said, “you arrive at solutions by such brilliant shortcuts that I feel like an old cart horse stumbling along out of sight behind you. My models hitherto have been the classical detectives—”

“Tuts!” she laughed, “they were only men!”

“Yes,” I agreed, “we are not much of a sex. And now, guess again please, it’s a very simple conundrum this time—for you. Who was the man behind the wall—or the rocks?”

She looked the least trifle hurt.

“I am really trying to help,” she said.

“I know it!” I assured her. “And don’t think I am laughing at you. This jumping to conclusions is probably the right way of reaching them. Anyhow my way has failed, and I am only too keen to try yours.”

But I could see that I had a sensitive as well as a clever ally, and her ardour was evidently a little damped. I tried my best to rekindle it.

“I haven’t told you yet,” I said, “about Mr. Hobhouse’s attempts at detection. He discovered one little fact. The old man with the tinted spectacles was seen by a small child running towards the beach after he had interviewed me.”

I could see her pricking up her ears again, but she said little this time, and I went on to tell her of Bolton’s two talks with me. When I came to his discovery her ardour was fairly aflame again, yet she still seemed to be holding herself in a little.

“Someone who hasn’t lived all ‘their’ life in the place,” she repeated. “Yes, it sounds as if he meant a woman.”

“Oh, I didn’t say that,” I interposed.

“You thought it,” she retorted, “and in that case I suppose it was me.”

“But surely he must have known that before!”

“One would think so,” she said thoughtfully, “but he didn’t look a very intelligent man—poor fellow! Still, it would be a stupid kind of discovery to make a fuss about.”

“There’s just one thing more to tell you,” I said; and I told her of the curious episode by the cliffs on the day Bolton was murdered, and mentioned my own conclusions, such as they were, and my difficulties in fitting them into the evidence.

There was no doubt about her keenness now, yet I noticed that there were no bold inferences this time. Nor did she even ask me many questions. But I saw her grow very thoughtful.

“Well,” I said, “have you any ideas—any suspicions?”

She gave no answer for a few moments, and then she said.

“I am not going to jump to conclusions again, Mr. Merton. There is no use trying to act on wild ideas till we have found a little more out. You might just be running risks for no purpose, and you are in quite enough danger as it is.”

“Hobhouse will look after me,” I assured her.

She glanced at me with a look in her eyes that gave me a little thrill, and then I saw a slight shiver run over her.

“You are too brave to realise what danger you are in! Remember Bolton!”

“Believe me, Miss Rendall, I am just as careful of my skin as other people, but there is absolutely no danger so long as they don’t spot me.”

“But how long will that be? And you are taking no precautions at all!”

“But I am! I assure you I am. I have a code wire arranged with my cousin and when he gets the message ‘Request permission to be visited by my own doctor,’ he will be in Ransay as fast as he can steam.”

She gave a little laugh, but looked anxious still.

“What a delicious message! Well, that’s better than nothing. But you don’t imagine they will give you warning, do you?”

“You will,” I said confidently. “When you guess there’s danger I’ll wire. And now, I hope you have some idea in your head besides this notion of my danger. Be honest! what’s in your mind?”

But I now perceived I had also an obstinate ally.

“I have told you,” she persisted, “we must find out a little more before doing anything rash. And I promise not to keep anything back, and to tell you at once if I find out anything worth knowing. Oh, if you only knew how I want you to catch those people! As if I could possibly do anything again to interfere with you!”

What I should have liked to do was to take her hands and say something very friendly. What I did do was to thank her and assure her I trusted her, in words that I think she knew were sincere; and arrange to see her accidentally next day. And then I set off for my sanatorium with thoughts that were not in the least of the detective type.

It was Jean Rendall’s eyes, voice, smile and face—herself from her hair to her ankles—that filled my mind as I hummed my way home. Unlike the suspicious stranger, Thomas Sylvester Hobhouse had not been given to singing, whistling, or humming as he walked, but he broke loose now. I had instinctively dreaded a too close acquaintance with that girl while the case was doubtful. I felt in my bones she would be dangerous. Now I was enraptured to discover she was fatal.

XV

Part of the Truth

I never remember feeling more intensely chagrined than when I reached our bleak house twenty minutes late for our early dinner to find the doctor had eaten a hurried meal quarter of an hour before the usual hour and rushed out to attend an urgent case.

I asked at once whether he had been told of the pocket book. Yes, it appeared he had. He had seemed very interested, but had immediately ordered his dinner hour to be advanced and then hurried away without putting further questions.

Was his haste a consequence of what he was told, or merely a coincidence? Well, I was resolved to leave that point in doubt no later than his return. I hardly debated at all the question of what to do. The baffling business of groping in the dark, and daily scheming to discover a window, without giving myself away, had gone on long enough. I had found a head at last and I meant to hit it. It might turn out to be the wrong head; still, I felt convinced I could scarcely fail to discover something fresh.

But though I proposed to take a bold course and make a shortcut to the heart of this infernal mystery, I realised perfectly that if the cut actually led me there, it would prove an exceedingly dangerous byway. It was such a gamble that I shrank from summoning my cousin until it had come off, but I wrote out the code telegram we had arranged and put it in my pocket ready for emergencies. Of the doctor’s two servants the younger anyhow was absolutely trustworthy I was convinced, and I meant to send her with the wire to the post office while I kept guard over the prisoner. And then, to ensure there being a prisoner, I saw that all the chambers of my revolver were loaded and put it in my coat pocket ready to my hand.

The afternoon dragged on, the wind still blustering round the house and the hail now and then rattling on the windows; but no Dr. Rendall appeared. Tea time arrived and still no sign of him. I gave him half an hour’s grace and then had my own tea and returned to the smoking-room. The evening by this time had fallen and the curtains were drawn and the lamps lit.

And then at last I heard him enter the front door. I jumped up and, with a dramatic instinct for taking the centre of the stage, placed myself before the fire, but I heard him run upstairs and it was some minutes before the sound of his descending steps reached me. The moment the door opened I was conscious that one of those peculiar changes I had so often noticed had taken place in the man. He smiled at me, but with a curiously furtive eye, and then he shut the door and came forward.

“You have had tea, I hope,” said he.

I wasted no time in preliminaries. Keeping my right hand closed over the revolver in my pocket I held out the pocket book with my left.

“Dr. Rendall,” I said, “you have heard that Bolton’s pocket book has been found. Here it is. Kindly look at that entry.”

The man started perceptibly and stared at me. Speaking in that tone and without my eye glasses I must have made an astonishing contrast to the Thomas Hobhouse he had last seen that morning at breakfast.

“Read that,” I commanded.

He took the pocket book and I watched him closely. I saw his eyebrows rise as he read.

“What’s all this about?” he asked.

“It is Bolton’s last entry in his note book before he was murdered, and it means that O’Brien is either still in this island, or that a confederate of his is playing traitor in his place, and that one of the two has just committed murder. It is quite impossible that you don’t know something of this!”

His blue eyes now had considerably more anger than guilt in them. In fact I was bound to admit that he looked a fine upstanding man, with his grey moustache, high colour, and an air of unmistakable indignation in his face.

“Who the devil are you?” he demanded.

“I may tell you that I am not Thomas Sylvester Hobhouse, and that I have never taken liquor enough in my life to hurt myself. I am here to investigate certain things that have been going on in this island, and I’ll put one question to you straight, Dr. Rendall. You remember being visited by a certain man Merton last August. When you heard him approaching your house why did you pull down your blind?”

That shot went straight home. All the indignation vanished and I saw on the instant I had him at my mercy.

“What—what—has that to do with it?” he stammered.

“Don’t trouble to try and hedge. As a matter of fact I am Merton and I saw the blind go down myself. Since then we have always been on your tracks, Dr. Rendall.”

“I swear that that had nothing to do with treason!”

“You are accused of treason, your relations to O’Brien were very peculiar, and if you can’t explain that blind and this entry and a number of other things, you will be in an extremely nasty position.”

The doctor made no further effort to stand up to me. He sank into a chair while I stood over him, and I knew I was going to hear the truth at last. And yet this sudden collapse, and indeed his whole attitude, were so unexpected that I felt more puzzled than triumphant.

“Mr. Merton,” he said, “for God’s sake don’t give me away and I’ll tell you the whole truth. My cousin Philip can confirm it—or at least part of it. I came up here because—well, I’d married the wrong woman and gone off the rails a bit and Philip settled me here to keep me straight. I had debts too—I have them still, I may tell you frankly. That’s why I took in O’Brien. I wasn’t supposed to keep any liquor in the house—that was one of the conditions. But damn it, I wasn’t born to be a teetotaler, and that’s the plain truth, Mr. Merton. That devil O’Brien found me out and started to blackmail me—”

“Blackmail?” I asked.

“In his own way. He made me give him liquor—and there we were the pair of us! That’s why I pulled down the blind. The decanter and glasses were all out on this table here! And that’s why O’Brien was afraid you might be sent by his relations. That was the one thing he was afraid of—that he might be found out and taken away.”

I bent over him and sniffed.

“You have had a dram now!” I exclaimed.

“And it’s not the first since you’ve been here either. You see I’m perfectly frank with you, Mr. Merton. If you like to give me away to Philip—well be d⸺d, you can if you like. But you’ll surely not? I’ve told you what I’ve told to no one else.”

There rushed into my mind confirmation enough of part at least of the poor devil’s story. His curious moods, his manner as he entered the room this evening, O’Brien’s impish allusions to liquor when I first visited the house, all fell into their places now. Yet utterly as this had exploded my hopes, I think I was more glad than sorry to see the doctor come out of the ordeal with only this kind of stain on his character. He was a likeable man, we had been capital friends—and he was Jean’s cousin.

“I promise you, doctor,” I said, “that I shall repeat no word of this story—except of course in confidence to those who are on the track of this business in Ransay. Only in return you must tell me absolutely frankly if you have seen any grounds for suspecting O’Brien of anything treasonable—anything whatever.”

The doctor shook his head emphatically.

“The only plotting the man was capable of was to get liquor. Otherwise he was just a gas bag. I’ve seen him too often in a state when he’d have given everything away, if there had been anything to give.”

And then I remembered the pocket book.

“But this entry!” I cried. “How do you explain that?”

The doctor looked at it again and his bewilderment was obviously sincere.

“I’m frankly d⸺d if I can make head or tail of it,” he said. “Bolton must have got on the wrong scent; that’s the only thing I can imagine.”

And then, like a sharp smack in the face, Jean’s reading of that entry came back to me. Could she have guessed right after all? It looked uncommonly like it.

“And yet,” I said to myself, “it’s a great thing to have tested the other hypothesis.”

In fact, if one is not built to be easily dispirited, well, it is not easy to dispirit one. I looked at the doctor, and something in my expression seemed to make him smile. When he smiled he looked so pleasant that my conscience smote me. I told myself he certainly deserved some reparation for the ordeal I had put him through.

“Doctor,” I said, “I am devilish thirsty myself after this bout. Let’s each have a whisky and soda!”

It may or may not have been the wisest suggestion to make. I am not an expert in these matters. But anyhow if he enjoyed his drink as much as I enjoyed mine, it was at least a happy idea.

We had lit our pipes with our glasses at our sides, and I was in the midst of giving the doctor some further reparation in the shape of the true tale of my adventures, when I saw him suddenly start and glance guiltily at his tumbler.

“Is that someone in the hall?” he exclaimed.

“Probably the servants,” I suggested.

The next instant the door opened and, without any announcement, in walked my uncle Sir Francis Merton followed by my cousin Commander John Whiteclett.